<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Assorted things</title>
    <link>https://rafaelmenmell.netlify.com/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Assorted things</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 14 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Are pollen forecast good enough?</title>
      <link>https://rafaelmenmell.netlify.com/2019/02/14/are-pollen-forecast-good-enough/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/02/14/are-pollen-forecast-good-enough/</guid>
      <description>Introduction Maybe some of you (in my huge audience) have the bad luck of being allergic to pollen like myself. Since mid-January to the end of June I have to live very close to my antihistamines. Here in Madrid where I live health authorities issue newsletters (by email) with observations and forecast.
Although the service has some deficiencies (like not being available in weekends and fairy days) I found it useful, but how good are the forecasts provided?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Developing a package to analyze data of the hospital morbidity survey</title>
      <link>https://rafaelmenmell.netlify.com/2018/10/20/developing-a-package-to-analyze-data-of-the-hospital-morbidity-survey/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 20 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/10/20/developing-a-package-to-analyze-data-of-the-hospital-morbidity-survey/</guid>
      <description>Introduction This post is going to be the most ambitious one so far. Months ago I decided to develope a R package from scratch to learn a little about the process. So I dug up some code I wrote and I got to the work. And of course, for a job like that you want to work properly so I followed R packages by Hadley Wickham
 The data My package downloads and gives functions to analyze data from the Hospital morbidity survey from Spanish National Institute of Statistics, this data is quite interesting for several reasons:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Text mining in R. A different approach to The Iliad</title>
      <link>https://rafaelmenmell.netlify.com/2018/10/16/text-mining-in-r-a-different-approach-to-the-iliad/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/10/16/text-mining-in-r-a-different-approach-to-the-iliad/</guid>
      <description>.col1 { columns: 1 400px; /* number of columns and width in pixels*/ -webkit-columns: 1 400px; /* chrome, safari */ -moz-columns: 1 400px; /* firefox */ } .col2 { columns: 2 200px; /* number of columns and width in pixels*/ -webkit-columns: 2 200px; /* chrome, safari */ -moz-columns: 2 200px; /* firefox */ } .col3 { columns: 3 100px; -webkit-columns: 3 100px; -moz-columns: 3 100px; }  Introduction This project is an attempt to get familiarity with text mining in R and I haven’t found a better way to get it that mining The Iliad.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>One tweet leads to some R work about births</title>
      <link>https://rafaelmenmell.netlify.com/2018/10/05/one-tweet-leads-to-some-r-work-about-births/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/10/05/one-tweet-leads-to-some-r-work-about-births/</guid>
      <description>This new post was born because of my curiosity about this tweet:
Italy 1960-2014: Big drop in annual number of births, big increase in ages of mothers. #Italy #fertility pic.twitter.com/QGT0AnA3IU — Carl Schmertmann (@CSchmert) 7 de febrero de 2018   Sometimes you just feel the urge to recreate some data analysis that you find interesting. Im my case I used data from Spain that I found in INE (National Institute of Statistics), with a little effort I found out the ftp where the data are hidden.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Funny facts about borrowed stuff in Madrid public libraries</title>
      <link>https://rafaelmenmell.netlify.com/2018/10/03/funny-facts-about-borrowed-stuff-in-madrid-public-libraries/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/10/03/funny-facts-about-borrowed-stuff-in-madrid-public-libraries/</guid>
      <description>As a regular user of Madrid public libraries I’m glad of having found data about borrowed stuff. So let’s take a look at it and answer a couple of questions.
Miguel de Cervantes Prize is one of the most richest literary prizes and the most prestigious of the prizes to writers in spanish.
So, what’s the impact in the popularity of a writer measured by the number of borrowing in public libraries?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Scrapping BOE in search of post election designations</title>
      <link>https://rafaelmenmell.netlify.com/2018/09/26/scrapping-boe-in-search-of-post-election-designations/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/09/26/scrapping-boe-in-search-of-post-election-designations/</guid>
      <description>Anyone with little contact with spanish adminstration, or just with interest in politics, knows that after a major change in the party ruling the goverment goes an important amount of dessignations in the highest levels of administration.
I want to quantify this by counting the dessignations and cessations published in BOE (Official State Gazette) with R.
suppressPackageStartupMessages(library(XML)) suppressPackageStartupMessages(library(ggplot2)) suppressPackageStartupMessages(library(dplyr)) CuentaNombramientos &amp;lt;- function(fecha){ path &amp;lt;- sprintf(&amp;quot;https://boe.es/diario_boe/xml.php?id=BOE-S-%s&amp;quot;,fecha) resumen_boe_xml &amp;lt;- XML::xmlParse(file = readLines(path)) top &amp;lt;- xmlRoot(resumen_boe_xml) if (xmlValue(top[[1]][[1]])!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>About</title>
      <link>https://rafaelmenmell.netlify.com/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 May 2016 21:48:51 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/about/</guid>
      <description>My name is Rafael Menéndez, almost 40 yo., father of two, forestry engineer, data analyst at Meteologica. Assorted interests: archeology, non-fiction literature, meteorology, ancient history, R, coding and much more.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
